Guide to the W.W.H. Davis Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Following the bombardment of Fort Sumter on April 12, 1861, the Doylestown Guards responded to President Lincoln's request for troops to defend the capital. Davis was commissioned captain of Company I, 25th Regiment, Pennsylvania Volunteers on April 26. Soon thereafter Davis and his men went to Harrisburg, where they joined the other companies of their regiment for training. On May 3 from Camp Scott in York, Pennsylvania, Davis wrote his wife that he had been placed in command of six companies, numbering some four hundred men. (Box 3, folder 43) He reported that his company, the Doylestown Guards, was the best outfitted, armed, and disciplined in camp.
The next week Davis received special orders from General Simon Cameron, Secretary of War, to detach the battery belonging to the Ringold Artillery and report to Colonel Cake in Washington. Davis with eighty men and four pieces of cannon departed York by railroad and reached the north side of Baltimore early on the morning of May fifteenth. The battery of the Ringold Artillery was the first company to pass directly through the City of Baltimore since the bloody riot of April 19, in which Pennsylvania and Massachusetts troops were attacked by Southern sympathizers. In letters to his wife and father, Davis described in gripping detail the tension and fear he and his men experienced while passing through the cursing, taunting crowd. (Box 3, folder 43)
The battery arrived safely in Washington and was attached to the Advance Pennsylvania Regiment, nicknamed the Cameronians, after Secretary of War Cameron. Toward the end of June, Davis and his men were sent to the upper Potomac, some fifty miles above Washington in northwestern Maryland, to reinforce the column of Colonel Stone. They passed through Rockville, Poolsville, and Point-of-Rocks before reaching Harper's Ferry. Occasionally they engaged in brief skirmishes with rebel forces but never actually came into battle. From Williamsport they crossed over the Potomac to Martinsburg, Virginia (now West Virginia) to reinforce General Patterson. From there they went to Winchester, Virginia, and then back to Charlestown, Virginia (now West Virginia), where Davis was made provost marshall of the town. On August 1 the term of Davis's three-month enlistment expired. Upon special orders of the secretary of war, Davis returned home, where he raised the 104th Regiment of the Pennsylvania Volunteers.
By the fall Davis had returned to Washington. He was stationed at Camp Davis in Kalorama Heights, named in honor of his father, and commanded the 3rd Provisional Brigade, numbering some thirty-two hundred men. In letters to his father he constantly urged him to use his influence to help secure him a brigadier generalship. These letters accomplished little, but as a "pet" of the secretary of war, he was introduced to such notables as General McClellan and the Count de Paris. In a letter of February 2, 1862 to his father, Davis expressed his fears of being passed over and missing the glories of battle. (Box 3, folder 47) Around the end of March Davis was ordered to accompany General McClellan in his campaign to take Richmond. His letters provide a detailed account of the transport of the troops from Alexandria to Fortress Monroe, as well as ensuing skirmishes and battles.
During the campaign Davis and his men were constantly on the march, frequently separated from their baggage, forced to sleep in their clothes in the open and to subsist on hard crackers, as well as being shot at by the enemy. By the end of the month, when his regiment was within six miles of the Richmond, he was wounded in the arm and sent home to recover. Davis returned to active duty in August, but the Union army was now in retreat and evacuating the peninsula. Around the end of the month Davis was placed in command of the fort at Gloucester Point, just across the river from Yorktown. He set about repairing and strengthening this stronghold, where he remained until the end of the year.
In January 1863 Davis's brigade was shipped to Carolina City, North Carolina, but by the end of the month they were transferred to Hilton Head Island, South Carolina. In early July Davis and his men were sent to Folly Island in Charleston Harbor to take part in the siege of Charleston. General Gillmore placed Davis in command of all the Union forces on Folly Island, which was the base of supplies for operations against Charleston. For the next year Davis variously served on Folly, Morris, and James Island and he carefully recorded events and observations in his letters and in a journal. On July 6, 1864, Davis was in a tree examining the position of the rebel forces with his field glasses when a shell exploded near him. The resulting injury cost him most of the fingers of his right hand. For W. W. H. Davis the war was over and he was mustered out on September 30, 1864.
In addition to correspondence, the scrapbooks also contain photographs of Davis, his wife, Harvard Law School, and various public buildings in Monterey, Mexico; newspaper clippings, especially published letters written by Davis about the Mexican War; some broadsides in Spanish from Davis's civil service in New Mexico; a few crude, hand-drawn maps; a number of receipts; and twenty-six captioned pencil drawings depicting scenes from the siege of Charleston. See appendix for a list of these drawings.
Series II, Autobiographical Writings, reflects Davis's involvement in and impressions of Mexico and the American Southwest. The series contains an essay on the occupation of Mexico City by American forces during the Mexican War and another on the Spaniard in New Mexico. There are numerous draft fragments describing the Mexican War. The series also contains a lengthy letter to an unidentified editor in which Davis rebuts a letter of William Ellery Channing to Henry Clay on the question of Texas annexation. The greatest portion of the series consists of a memoir, written by Davis in 1849, recounting his experiences as captain and aide-de-camp to Brigadier General Caleb Cushing during the Mexican War. There are two typescript copies of this memoir.
Series III, Personal Papers, consists of an extra-illustrated Life of John Davis, journals, a ledger, and miscellaneous papers reflecting Davis's travels and responsibilities in New Mexico and military service in the Mexican War and Civil War. Davis kept journals of a trip west in 1852 and his 1853 journey from Doylestown to Santa Fe. A ledger documents Davis's service as Santa Fe agent for Hockaday and Hall. Davis also kept a journal during the siege of Charleston in 1863-64. Pamphlets of the Aztec Club and the National Association of the Veterans of the Mexican War provide evidence of Davis's affiliation with Mexican War veterans's associations. There is also a student notebook in Spanish.
Oversize consists of official appointments to civil service in the Territory of New Mexico and commissions to military service in the Mexican War, Pennsylvania State Militia, and the Civil War.
Appendix: LIST OF SIEGE OF CHARLESTON DRAWINGS
1. "Secessionville and adjacent Rebel Works, James Island, S.C." [Hoffmann] (Box 3, folder 43)
2. "Mount Pleasant, Sullivan's Island, S.C." [unsigned] (Box 3, folder 47)
3. "Camp of 104th Pennsylvania Regiment, Morris Island, S.C., 1863-64" [unsigned] (Box 4, folder 50)
4. "Castle Pickney, Charleston Harbor, Morris Island, S.C., Nov. 19, 1863" [Otto Enz Rgt., Enfants Perdus, N.Y.V.] (Box 4, folder 50)
5. "Fort Ripley, floating battery, Charleston Harbor, Morris Island, Nov. 20, 1863" [Otto Enz Rgt., Enfants Perdus, N.Y.V.] (Box 4, folder 50)
6. "Quarters of Col. W. W. H. Davis, and Guard Mounting, Morris Island, S.C." [unsigned] (Box 4, folder 53)
7. "Beacon House, Morris Island, S.C." [unsigned] (Box 4, folder 54)
8. "View in Battery Chatfield, during Bombardment of Sumter" [Hoffmann] (Box 4, folder 55)
9. "Fort Wagner as seen From the Fifth Parallel, Morris Island, S.C." [Otto Enz Rgt., Enfants Perdus] (Box 4, folder 55)
10. "Light House Inlet, from Ordnance Yard, Morris Island, S.C." [unsigned] (Box 4, folder 56)
11. "Opening the Trenches, Morris Island, S.C." [unsigned] (Box 4, folder 56)
12. "The Marblehead," "The Wabash," "New Ironsides," "Monitor Lehigh, showing effect of shots," "English Blockade Runner" [Otto Enz Regt., Enfants Perdus] (Box 4, folder 56)
13. "Head Quarters of Col. Davis, Commanding U.S. Forces, Morris Island, S.C." [unsigned] (Box 4, folder 57)
14. "Inside of Fort Wagner, Rebel Battery, Charleston, S.C., As it was left on Evacuation, Nov. 7, 1863" [Otto Enz Regt., Enfants Perdus] (Box 4, folder 57)
15. "Bursted Three hundred Pounder, Morris Island, S.C." [unsigned] (Box 4, folder 57)
16. "Mortar Battery, in Chatfield, Morris Island, S.C." [unsigned] (Box 4, folder 58)
17. "Fourth Bombardment of Fort Sumter, Charleston, S.C., As it appeared, November 18, 1863" [Otto Enz Regt., Enfants Perdus, N.Y.V.] (Box 4, folder 58)
18. "Interior view of Battery Purviance, Morris Island, S.C." [unsigned] (Box 4, folder 58)
19. "Battery, North End Folly Island, S.C." [unsigned] (Box 4, folder 59)
20. "Exterior View of the Sally-port, Fort Wagner, Morris Island, S.C." [Otto Enz Regt., Enfants Perdus, N.Y.V.] (Box 4, folder 59)
21. "View from Craig Hill, Looking North, Morris Island, S.C." [Hoffmann] [on reverse, same title with date of Feby 2nd 1864] (Box 4, folder 59)
22. "Battery Marshal, Sullivan's Island, S.C." [Hoffmann] [on reverse, same title with date of January 16th 1864] (Box 4, folder 59)
23. "Fort Putnam, formerly Gregg, Morris Island, S.C." [Hoffmann] [on reverse, same title with addition: "Charleston and Rebel Fortifications in distance"] (Box 4, folder 60)
24. "Payne's Dock with Confederate Batteries in the Distance" [unsigned] [on reverse, same title with addition: "'Bull of the woods' in distance on the left, Morris Island, S.C., Feb'y 6th 1864"] (Box 4, folder 60)
25. "Fort Shaw, Morris Island, S.C." [Hoffmann] [on reverse, same title with date of Feb'y 5th 1864] (Box 4, folder 61)
26. "Fort Strong, formerly Wagner, Morris Island, S.C." [Hoffmann] [on reverse, same title with date of Feb'y 9th 1864] (Box 4, folder 61)
Democrat (Doylestown, Pa.); Santa Fe Gazette; Apache Indians; Buena Vista, Battle of, Mexico, 1847; Civil service -- United States; Indians of North America -- Government relations; Indians of North America -- New Mexico; Mexican War, 1846-1848; Monterrey, Battle of, Monterrey, Mexico, 1846; Mormons -- New Mexico; Navajo Indians; Patronage, Political -- United States; Political parties -- United States; Press and politics -- United States; Press, Political party; Indians of North America -- Utah; Charleston (S.C.) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Davidsville (Pa.) -- Description and travel; Doylestown (Pa.) -- Description and travel; Fort Sumter (Charleston, S.C.); Maryland -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Mexico City (Mexico) -- History -- American occupation, 1847-1848; New Mexico -- Description and travel; New Mexico -- History -- 1848-; New Mexico -- Politics and government -- 1848-1950; North Carolina -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Pennsylvania -- Description and travel; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1861-1865; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- Description and travel; Santa Fe (N.M.) -- Description and travel; South Carolina -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- Politics and government -- 1849-1861; Veracruz (Veracruz-Llave, Mexico); Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Washington (D.C.) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; West (U.S.); West Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Albumen prints; Diaries -- United States; Drawings -- United States; Photographic prints; Photographs -- 19th century; Editors -- United States; Historians -- United States; Lawyers -- Pennsylvania; Soldiers -- United States; Life of John Davis; Blair, John; Collins, James L.; Cushing, Caleb, 1800-1879; Davis, Anna Carpenter, -1884; Davis, Elizabeth N.; Davis, John, 1788-1878; Davis, W. W. H. (William Watts Hart), 1820-1910; Fox, Edward J.; Longhead, Joseph Pfeiffer; Mercur, Sarah S. Davis; Meriwether, Davis; Partridge, Alden, 1785-1854; Wilson, Oliver Howard; Davis family; United States. Army ( Military life); United States. Army ( Officers); United States. Department of the Treasury -- Officials and employees; Democratic Party (N.M.); Democratic Party (Pa.); Democratic Party (U.S.)
- Scrapbooks, 1846-81; Series I; 1.25; (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Scrapbooks, is divided into five subseries, each of which represents one of Davis's original volumes.
  - LETTERS TO W. W. H. DAVIS, 1846-57
    - Incoming: family and non-family
      - Correspondence, 1846 Dec (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, 1847 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, 1847 Apr-May (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence, 1847 Jun-Jul (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, 1847 Aug-Sep (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence, 1847 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence, 1848 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence, 1848 Apr-Dec (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence, 1849-50 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, 1851-52 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence, 1853-54 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence, 1856-57 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - CIVIL SERVICE IN NEW MEXICO, 1853-57
    - Incoming: non-family
      - Correspondence, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence, 1854-55 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Correspondence, 1856 Jan-Sep (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Correspondence, 1856 Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Correspondence, 1857 Jan-Feb (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Correspondence, 1857 Mar-May (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Correspondence, 1857 Jun (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Correspondence, 1857 Jul-Aug (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Correspondence, 1857 Sep (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Correspondence, 1857 Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Correspondence, 1858 Jan-Mar (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Correspondence, 1858 Apr-Nov (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Correspondence, 1859-60 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Correspondence, 1881-84 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Outgoing: family
      - Correspondence, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Correspondence, 1855 Feb-Jul (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Correspondence, 1855 Aug-Dec (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Correspondence, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - Correspondence, 1857 Feb-Apr (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Correspondence, 1857 May-Aug (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - WARTIME FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE, VOL. I
    - Mexican War. Outgoing: family
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1847 Jan-Feb (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Correspondence, 1847 Mar-Apr (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1847 May-Jun (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1847 Jul-Aug (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1847 Sep-Dec (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1848 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1848 May (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1875 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Civil War. Outgoing: family
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1861 Apr-May (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Correspondence, 1861 Jun (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1861 Jul (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - Correspondence, 1861 Nov-Dec (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1862 Jan-Mar (Box 3, Folder 47)
      - Correspondence, 1862 Apr (Box 3, Folder 48)
      - Correspondence, 1862 May (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - WARTIME FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE, VOL. II
    - Civil War. Outgoing: family
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1862 Jul-Aug (Box 4, Folder 50)
      - Correspondence, 1862 Sep-Oct (Box 4, Folder 51)
      - Correspondence, 1862 Nov-Dec (Box 4, Folder 52)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1863 Jan-Feb (Box 4, Folder 53)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1863 Mar-Apr (Box 4, Folder 54)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1863 May-Jun (Box 4, Folder 55)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1863 Jul-Aug (Box 4, Folder 56)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1863 Sep-Oct (Box 4, Folder 57)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1863 Nov-Dec (Box 4, Folder 58)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1864 Jan-Feb (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1864 Mar-Apr (Box 4, Folder 60)
      - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1864 May-Jul (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - MILITARY CORRESPONDENCE WITH W. W. H. DAVIS, 1861-64
    - Incoming: non-family
      - Correspondence, 1861 Apr-May (Box 5, Folder 62)
      - Correspondence, 1861 Jun-Jul (Box 5, Folder 63)
      - Correspondence, 1861 Aug (Box 5, Folder 64)
      - Correspondence, 1861 Sep (Box 5, Folder 65)
      - Correspondence, 1861 Oct (Box 5, Folder 66)
      - Correspondence, 1862 (Box 5, Folder 67)
      - Correspondence, 1863 (Box 5, Folder 68)
      - Correspondence, 1864-65 (Box 5, Folder 69)
      - Correspondence, 1871-79 (Box 5, Folder 70)
      - Correspondence, 1880 (Box 5, Folder 71)
- Autobiographical Writings, 1849-88; Series II; 0.75; (2 boxes)
  Series II, Autobiographical Writings, is arranged alphabetically.
  - "The Halls of the Montezumas": draft, holograph, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - "The Journal of a Volunteer Officer in the Mexican War by W. W. H. Davis, Captain and Aide-de-Camp of Brigadier General Cushing, 1846-48, Doylestown, Pennsylvania"
    - Draft, holograph, 1849 (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Draft, typescript, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 74-79)
    - Draft, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 80-83)
    - Draft, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 84-86)
  - Mexican War, description of: draft fragments, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 87-88)
  - "The Spaniard in New Mexico": printed version, 1888 (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Texas, Annexation of: rebuttal by W. W. H. Davis to Mr. Channing's letter to Mr. Clay: draft, holograph, 1849 Oct 7 (Box 7, Folder 90)
- Personal Papers, 1822-1921; Series III; 0.5; (2 boxes)
  Series III, Personal Papers, is divided into four subseries: Extra-Illustrated Life of John Davis, Journals, Ledger, and Miscellaneous Papers. Within each subseries the material is arranged alphabetically.
  - EXTRA-ILLUSTRATED LIFE OF JOHN DAVIS
    - Letters to John Davis from
      - Wright, Silas, 1866 Sep 12 (Box 7a, Folder 90a)
      - Ziegler, Jacob, 1841 Oct 26 (Box 7a, Folder 90a)
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Box 8, folder 90b
    - Letters to W. W. H. Davis from
      - Belville, J., 1886 Nov 10 (Box 7a, Folder 90a)
      - Carell, J. B., 1898 Jul 29 (Box 7a, Folder 90a)
        Encloses letter to Carell from Thomas J. Beans, 1898 Jul 26.
      - Chapman, Henry, 1886, 1889 (Box 7a, Folder 90a)
      - Davis, John, 1833 Jan 30 (Box 7a, Folder 90a)
      - Kelley, William D., 1887 Jan 19 (Box 7a, Folder 90a)
      - Lundy, John P., 1886 Oct 8 (Box 7a, Folder 90a)
      - Paxon, Edward M., [1887] (Box 7a, Folder 90a)
      - Wright, C. E., 1886 Nov 20 (Box 7a, Folder 90a)
    - Miscellaneous
      - 47 engravings of American historical figures, maps of battles, 1822-68 (Box 7a, Folder 90a)
      - 42 albumen photographs of American historical figures, family members, local buildings, n.d. (Box 7a, Folder 90a)
      - Clippings of obituaries of family members, review of the Life of John Davis, 1888-1921 (Box 7a, Folder 90a)
      - Writings: obituaries, genealogical chart of William Simpson, extract of a letter from S. S. Davis to W. W. H. Davis, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 90b)
  - JOURNALS
    - Journal of a trip to the West, 1852 (Box 8, Folder 91)
    - Journal of a trip from Doylestown, Pennsylvania, to Santa Fé, New Mexico, 1853 (Box 8, Folder 92)
    - Private Journal of the attack on Charlestown, South Carolina, by W. W. H. Davis, Colonel, 104th Pennsylvania Volunteers, Commander of 1st Brigade, 2nd Division, 18th Army Corps, 1863 Apr (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - LEDGER
    - W. W. H. Davis, agent, in account with Hockaday and Hall, stage proprietors, Independence, Missouri, to Santa Fe, New Mexico, 1854 (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS
    - "The Constitution of the Aztec Club of 1847 and List of Members" [pamphlet], 1896 (Box 8, Folder 95)
    - "Fifth Annual Reunion of the National Association of the Veterans of the Mexican War" [pamphlet], 1878 (Box 8, Folder 96)
    - Student notebook in Spanish, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 97)
- Oversize, 1846-66; 2; (1 box)
  Oversize is divided into two sections: Appointments and Commissions. Within each section the material is arranged chronologically.
  - APPOINTMENTS
    - U.S. District Attorney for the Territory of New Mexico, 1853 Sep 19 (Box 9, Folder 98)
    - U.S. District Attorney for the Territory of New Mexico, 1854 Mar 14 (Box 9, Folder 99)
    - Secretary of the Territory of New Mexico, 1854 May 22 (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - COMMISSIONS
    - First Lieutenant of Company E in the First Regiment of the Massachusetts Infantry, 1846 Dec 31 (Box 9, Folder 101)
    - Captain of the Doylestown Guards of the Uniformed Militia of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, 1859 Jun 6 (Box 9, Folder 102)
    - Captain of Company I in the 25th Regiment of the Pennsylvania Volunteers of the Uniformed Militia of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, 1861 Apr 26 (Box 9, Folder 103)
    - Brigadier General by Brevet, U.S. Volunteers, 1866 May 22 (Box 9, Folder 104)